Guide to the South Brooklyn Savings Bank records 2007.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
South Brooklyn Savings Bank records
Bulk, 1850-1980
1850-2007
2007.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
21.5 linear feet in 19 boxes of various sizes and five loose objects
The collection consists of the records of the Board of Trustees of the South Brooklyn Savings Bank (originally known as the South Brooklyn Savings Institution, and later known as the Independence Savings Bank and the Independence Community Bank). These records include Board meeting minutes, financial records and reports, administrative files, photographs, scrapbooks, and memorabilia. The records span the entire history of the bank, from its founding in 1850 through 2006 (the year the bank was acquired by Sovereign Bank).
Independence Community Bank (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).
Independence Savings Bank (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).
South Brooklyn Savings Bank.
South Brooklyn Savings Institution (New York, N.Y.).
Historical Note
The South Brooklyn Savings Institution was founded in Brooklyn, New York, in 1850. The institution formally changed its name to the South Brooklyn Savings Bank in 1930. The bank's main branch was located at the corner of Atlantic Avenue and Court Street. Another major branch was located at 18th Avenue and 65th Street. The bank expanded throughout the 20th century, with offices located in Brooklyn, Queens, Manhattan, the Bronx, and Nassau County, New York. In 1975, the bank formally changed its name to the Independence Savings Bank. In 1992, "the bank reorganized into [a] mutual holding company." The bank underwent further reorganization in 1997, and formally changed its name to Independence Community Bank Corp. In 2006, the bank was acquired by Sovereign Bancorp, Inc.
Sources
South Brooklyn Savings Bank One Hundredth Anniversary booklet, 1950
Certificate of name change, 1930
Independence Savings Bank financial statement, 1975
Independence Community Bank Corp. - U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission report, 2000
Arrangement note
The collection is organized into five series:
Series 1: Board of Trustees meeting minutes
Series 2: Financial records
Series 3: Administrative files
Series 4: Photographs and Scrapbooks
Series 5: Memorabilia
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of the records of the Board of Trustees of the South Brooklyn Savings Bank (originally known as the South Brooklyn Savings Institution, and later known as the Independence Savings Bank and the Independence Community Bank). These records include Board meeting minutes, financial records and reports, administrative files, photographs, scrapbooks, and memorabilia. The records span the entire history of the bank, from its founding in 1850 through 2006 (the year the bank was acquired by Sovereign Bank).
Conditions Governing Access note
Open to users without restriction.
Related Archival Materials note
Brooklyn Historical Society holds the following related collections:
Independence Community Bank oral histories, 2006-2007 (2008.032)
South Brooklyn Savings Institution trustees photographic portrait albums, 1850-1922 (ARC.215).
Independence Community Bank Presidential Portrait Collection, 1850-1973 (M2007.023)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Independence Community Bank Corp., 2007.
Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation.; Independence Community Bank (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Independence Savings Bank (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; South Brooklyn Savings Bank.; South Brooklyn Savings Institution (New York, N.Y.).; Sovereign Bancorp.; Advertising |x Banks and banking; Annual reports; Artifacts (object genre); Awards; Bank employees |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Banks and banking |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baseball |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baseballs (ball); Basketball |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bowling |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Commerce; Business records; Clippings (information artifacts); Community banks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Deeds; Ephemera; Financial records; Financial statements; Interviews; Minutes; Mortgages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Photographs; Portraits; Reports; Savings banks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Sports |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tax records; Trophies (objects)
- Series 1: Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1850-1966
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains four bound volumes of Board of Trustee meeting minutes (1850-1935) and two bound volumes of Executive Committee meeting minutes (1877-1966), which document the decision-making and policies which led to the bank's success and expansion from 1850 to 1966.
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes (2 volumes), 1850-1917 (Box 14, Folder -)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1917-1933 (Box 13, Folder -)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes, 1933-1935 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1877-1920 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1958-1966 (Box 8, Folder -)
- Series 2: Financial records, 1850-2000
  The series contains financial records and reports dating from 1850 to 2000. It includes financial ledgers (1850-1944), tax documents (1922-1934, 1952-1954), Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation reports (1953-1975), reports to the Board of Trustees (1958-1981), and financial statements (1960-1992, 2000).
  Arrangement note
  The series is generally arranged chronologically by date.
  - Monthly Reports ledger, 1850-1901 (Box 12, Folder -)
  - Organizational and financial ledger, circa 1895-1931 (Box 10, Folder -)
    General note
    Ledger contains a mix of organizational and financial records. The following items are listed in its index: Organization of bank, Trustees when elected, Offices, Interest to depositors, Panics, Amount due depositors, Bonds and mortgages, Employees of bank, Finances committees, Executive committees, Examining committees, Interest on securities, and Receipt and payments from 1850
  - Financial journal, 1933 (Box 12, Folder -)
  - Petty Cash ledger, 1933-1934 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Daily Record ledger, 1944 (Box 11, Folder -)
  - Daily Record ledger, 1946 (Box 11, Folder -)
  - Expense journal - Tax subdivision - Bank buildings and operation, 1944 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Tax documents, 1923-1934 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Corporate Federal Income Tax Returns, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - FDIC reports and working papers (5 folders), 1943-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3-7)
  - FDIC reports and working papers (8 folders), 1969-1975 (Box 4, Folder 1-8)
  - Reports (5 folders), 1958-1981 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Financial statements, 1960-1992, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series 3: Administrative files, 1883-2006
  The series represents a small collection of files which were produced by the Board of Trustees and various administrative departments throughout the history of the bank, dating from 1883 to 2006.
  It contains property titles (1886-1892), public relations and advertising files (1937-2005), building and renovation files (1930-1964), copies of 1850 and 1859 articles of incorporaton, one file on the 2006 acquisition of the Independence Community Bank Corporation by Sovereign Bancorp, Inc., and other documents.
  The series is arranged chronologically by date.
  - Correspondence with NY State Superintendent of Banking Department, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Property titles, 1886-1892 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Organizational and financial ledger, circa 1895-1931 (Box 10, Folder -)
  - Branch Authorizations, 1930, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera, 1936-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Public Relations manual, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publications, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dormant Account Methods and Procedures survey, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Study Relating to the Monthly Publication of the South Brooklyn Savings Bank, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Retirement System, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Advertising - 100th Anniversary, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Educational materials, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Completed contracts, 1952-1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Building Committee, 1957-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1850 Act of Incorporation, 1859 amendment, and 1930 name change certificates, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Main office alterations, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mike Armstrong - Advertising files, 1975-2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Financial planning, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Stockholders - Merger meeting, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series 4: Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1883-2001
  The series contains photographs and scrapbooks documenting the bank from 1883 to 2001.
  It includes numerous photographic portraits of bank trustees, in three albums, five folders, and one framed photograph (circa 1940-2001). Additionally, the series contains two scrapbooks documenting the lives of trustees (1922-1982).
  It contains two clippings scrapbooks (1883-1920) and five advertising scrapbooks (1931-1953).
  Other photographs include bank baseball teams (circa 1930), the corner of Atlantic Avenue and Court Street (circa 1920), the bank's 90th anniversary (1940), Christmas celebrations (1951-1952), and bank openings (circa 1960).
  - Corner of Atlantic Avenue and Court Street photographs, circa 1920 (Box 17, Folder -)
  - South Brooklyn Savings Bank baseball team, circa 1930 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 90th anniversary photographs, 1940 (Box 17, Folder -)
  - Bank opening photographs (2 folders), circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Christmas photographs, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees portraits (3 folders), 1959-1979, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
  - Board of Trustees oversize portraits, 1970s (Box 17, Folder -)
  - Board of Trustees group photograph, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Trustees at NASDAQ MarketSite, Times Square (framed), circa 2000 (Box 16, Folder -)
  - Board of Trustees portrait albums (3 albums), circa 1940-1972 (Box 7, Folder -)
    Albums feature portraits of Board of Trustees dating back to 1850. The first and second albums appear to have been created around 1940, with additional material added to the albums until around 1972.
  - Board of Trustees scrapbooks (2 scrapbooks), 1922-1982 (Box 8, Folder -)
  - Clippings scrapbook, 1883-1923 (Box 8, Folder -)
  - Clippings scrapbook, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Folder -)
  - Advertising scrapbook, 1931-1937 (Box 16, Folder -)
  - Advertising and publicity scrapbook, 1943-1949 (Box 15, Folder -)
  - Advertising scrapbooks (3 scrapbooks), 1951-1953 (Box 15, Folder -)
- Series 5: Memorabilia, circa 1920s-2004
  The series contains bank memorabilia, dating from around the 1920s to 2004. It primarily consists of objects relating the bank's sports teams, including trophies for Brooklyn bank baseball, basketball, and bowling leagues (1930s and 1970s). Other objects include a wood block stamp of the bank's 18th Avenue branch building (circa 1920s-1940s), radio advertisment 12" vinyl records (circa 1950s), advertising awards (1970s), and paperweights commemorating the bank's stock valuations (1992-2004).
  - South Brooklyn Savings Bank 18th Avenue office building wood block stamp, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 17)
  - South Brooklyn Savings Bank championship team signed baseballs (2 objects), 1933-1934 (Box 19)
  - Savings Bank Baseball League of Brooklyn trophy, 1933-1935 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Savings Bank Baseball League of Brooklyn championship trophy, 1936 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Savings Bank Basketball League of Brooklyn championship trophy, 1934-1935 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Savings Bank Bowling League 2nd place trophy, 1976-1977 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Radio advertisements 12" vinyl records (2 records), circa 1950s (Box 17)
  - Eighth Annual Addy Awards - 1st place certificate, 1976 (Box 16)
  - Financial Advertising and Marketing Association - Town Crier Award, 1975 (Object Artifact shelf)
  - Commemorative paperweights (10 objects), 1992-2004 (Box 18)